L. Frank Baum Papers
L. Frank Baum Papers
1880 (ca.)-1975
1900-1942
Baum, L. Frank (Lyman Frank), 1856-1919
6.0 linear ft.
Biographical and genealogical material on the Baum and Gage families; material relating to the publishing history as well as the film and theatrical adaptations of The Wizard of Oz, including correspondence, manuscripts, reviews, publicity, and publications about Baum and Oz; photographs; and Oz memorabilia. Also, material pertaining to Russell P. MacFall and William W. Denslow.
148785
Biographical History
American author of children’s literature, native of Chittenango, N.Y.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Biographical and genealogical material on the Baum and Gage families; material relating to the publishing history as well as the film and theatrical adaptations of The Wizard of Oz, including correspondence, manuscripts, reviews, publicity, and publications about Baum and Oz; photographs; and Oz memorabilia. Also, material pertaining to Russell P. MacFall and William W. Denslow.
In 1980 the varied manuscript materials pertaining to L. Frank Baum, Russell MacFall and William Denslow in the Rare Book Division were transferred to the Manuscript Division, there to be combined with other Baum materials. Graduate students Dorothy Terino and Martha Maier found their semester Oz project turning into a year of work, culminating in an exhibit and the following inventory.
To the above have been added typescripts of L. Frank Baum, Frank J. Baum and Russell P. MacFall, as well as negatives and miscellaneous oversize illustrative materials.
Related Material
W. W. Denslow Collection
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- Children's; New York State; Baum, Frank Joslyn, 1883-1958.; Baum, L. Frank (Lyman Frank), 1856-1919.; Denslow, W. W. (William Wallace), 1856-1915.; MacFall, Russell P.; Gage family.; Baum family.; Authors, American.; Wizard of Oz.; Children’s literature, American.; Children’s literature -- Film and video adaptations.; Illustrated children’s books.; Illustrators -- United States; Book reviews.; Correspondence.; Genealogies (histories); Manuscripts for publication.; Memorabilia.; Obituaries.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Authors.; Illustrators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Genealogy - Baum and Gage Families
  - Baum Biographical Information (Box 1)
  - Published Biographical Information, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - L. Frank Baum - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Baum Family - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Chittenango (Box 1)
  - The Rose Lawn Home Journal (Box 1)
  - The Show Window. (Box 1)
  - Baum Writings (Box 1)
  - Correspondence from L. Frank Baum (Box 1)
  - Bankruptcy Cases - L. Frank Baum The Uplifters Club (Box 1)
  - L. Frank Baum - Obituaries and Tributes (Box 1)
  - Wills, L. Frank Baum, Maud G. Baum, Frank J. Baum, and Robert S. Baum (Box 1)
  - Maud Gage Baum (Mrs. L. Frank Baum) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence from Maud Gage Baum (Box 1)
- Theatre and Films
  - Early Theatrical Productions - Prior to Oz, 1880-1903 (Box 1)
  - Paul Tietjens - Biography and Photographs (Box 1)
  - Early Theatrical Productions - Wizard of Oz, 1902-1911 (Box 1)
  - Wizard of Oz - Photographs, 1902-1911 (Box 1)
  - Music and Lyrics, 1900-1913 (Box 2)
  - Early Theatrical Productions - Oz Sequels, 1905-1913 (Box 2)
  - Fairylogue and Radio Plays, 1908 (Box 2)
    - Photographs, 1908 (Box 2)
  - Early Films, 1913-1925 (Box 2)
  - The Wizard of Oz - film, 1939 (Box 2)
    - Photographs, 1939 (Box 2)
  - Late Theatrical Productions - Wizard of Oz, Post -1950 (Box 2)
  - The Wiz, 1975 (Box 2)
- Publishing
  - Publication History - The Wizard of Oz (Box 2)
  - Publishers
    - Way and Williams (Correspondence) (Box 2)
    - George M. Hill and George W. Ogilvie (Box 2)
    - Bobbs-Merrill (includes royalty information) (Box 2)
    - Reilly and Lee (formerly Reilly and Britton) (Box 2)
    - Reilly and Lee - correspondence with Maud Gage Baum (Box 2)
  - Copyright and other legal matters (Box 2)
  - Reviews of Baum Books (Box 2)
  - Reviews of Annotated Edition, reprints and reissues of Baum books (Box 2)
  - Publications about Oz (Box 2)
  - Book Publicity - Advertisements (Box 2)
  - The Ozmapolitan (Reilly and Lee) (Box 2)
  - Oz Playlets (Book Promotion) - scripts (Box 2)
  - Ruth Plumly Thompson (Box 2)
  - John R. Neill (Box 3)
  - Jack Snow (Box 3)
  - Rachel R. Cosgrove (Box 3)
  - Illustrations and Illustrators for Oz sequels (Box 3)
- MacFall
  - Russell P. MacFall (Box 3)
  - MacFall articles about Baum and Oz (Box 3)
  - To Please A Child
    See also L. Frank Baum: To Please a Child and material under Baum, Frank Joslyn and Russell P. MacFall
    - Related Material and Notes (Box 3)
    - Press Coverage (Box 3)
  - Correspondence From:
    - Frank J. Baum to R. MacFall, 1956; 1957,; 1958 (Box 3)
    - Mrs. Frank J. (Elizabeth) Baum to R. MacFall, 1958-1964 (Box 3)
  - MacFall Correspondence - Baum Relatives (Box 3)
  - Correspondence From:
    - Gage family to R. MacFall (Box 3)
    - [Martin] Gardner to R. MacFall and others (Box 3)
    - Greene brothers to R. MacFall (Box 3)
    - [Fred] Meyer to R. MacFall, 1953-1973; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - [Justin] Schiller to R. MacFall (Box 3)
    - [Eleanor Hall] Wilson to R. MacFall (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous to R. MacFall - A-Z (Box 3)
- Frank J. Baum
  - Frank J. Baum (general) (Box 3)
  - Correspondence from Frank J. Baum - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Harry Neal Baum - Correspondence (Box 3)
  - Bill Ubank (Box 3)
  - Dick Martin (Box 3)
- Fred Meyer
  - Fred Meyer - Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 4)
  - Robert R. Pattrick - Correspondence and other material (Box 4)
  - The International Wizard of Oz Club, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Oz-related greeting cards (Box 4)
  - Ozcot - Knox, Indiana (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous
  - Library Controversy (protest over removal of Oz book) L. Frank Baum Public School (Box 5)
  - Baum and Psychology (Box 5)
  - Oz Products (Box 5)
  - Oz-Inspired Events (Box 5)
  - Oz Games for Children (Box 5)
    See also Wizard of Oz Game Cards
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
- Denslow
  - William Wallace Denslow
    - Biography (Box 5)
    - Photographs (Box 5)
    - Book Publicity - Advertisements (Box 5)
    - Elbert Hubbard Association (Box 5)
  - Correspondence to MacFall from Doug Greene re: Denslow (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence re: Denslow (Box 5)
  - Wizard of Oz game cards designed by Denslow (Box 5)
  - Order blank illustrating Denslow's picture books (Box 5)
  - Reproductions of Denslow drawings (owned by Fred Meyer) (Box 5)
  - Denslow Illustrations (Box 5)
  - Denslow Illustrations - Life magazine abridged version of The Wonderful Wizard of Oz with Denslow illustrations (Box 5)
  - Correspondence to Denslow from Paul West (Box 5)
  - Article by Paul West (Denslow association) (Box 5)
- Typescripts
  - Baum, L. Frank
    - Wizard of Oz - typescript with music and lyrics (Box 6)
    - Girl from Oz (A musical comedy) - typescript, with directions (Box 6)
  - Baum, Frank J.
    - He Created the Wizard of Oz (To Please a Child, 1st version) - typescript (Box 6)
    - To Please a Child, 2nd version - typescript (t.p., introduction, 1st chapter, missing) (Box 6)
  - Baum, Frank Joslyn and Russell P. MacFall
    - Royal Historian of Oz: The life of L. Frank Baum, author of the Wizard of Oz (To Please a Child 3rd version) - typescript (Box 7)
    - To Please a Child, 4th version - typescript, 1960 (Box 7)
    - To Please a Child, 5th version - typescript, 1961 (Box 7)
- Negatives
  - Advertising handbill for new Wizard of Oz film (2 negs., 1 glass) (Box 7)
  - Anna Laughlin in Wizard, Fred Stone as Scarecrow (2 negs.) (Box 7)
  - Denslow at drawing board, plus 2 views of Paul Tietjens (Box 7)
  - Frank and Maud, brother Harry and Wife (1 neg) (Box 7)
  - Baum cottage as Macatawa, interior and exterior (on 1 negative) (Box 7)
  - Baum family (2 negs.) Maud B., Edna B., parents and brother (Box 7)
  - Baum family (2 negs.) (Box 7)
  - Ads for movie The Last Egyptian (Box 7)
  - Chorus girls in Wizard (2 negs.) (Box 7)
  - Baum portrait and text written as photographer Green took the picture (Box 7)
  - Drawings of and by Denslow, sketches of Montgomery and Stone (Box 7)
  - Macatawa cottage (3 views on 1 neg.) (Box 7)
  - Baum in garden at Ozcot, view of Ozcot (3 negatives) (Box 7)
  - Baum cottage at Macatawa (Box 7)
  - Oz Firm Manufacturing Company, Castorine can (2 negs.) (Box 7)
  - Maud Baum, Mrs. Brewster? (2 negs.) (Box 7)
  - Drawings of Fairylogue characters (broken glass negative) (Box 7)
- Oversize Illustrative Material
  - Map of the Marvelous Land of Oz (Oversize 1)
  - Showboat Wizard of Oz, Act 1 and 2, sets and characters (Oversize 2)
  - Showboat script for Wizard of Oz [and] Pinocchio (Oversize 2)
  - Cinderella, Heidi (Oversize 2)
  - Wizard of Oz coloring book (Swifts peanut butter, n.d.) (Oversize 2)
  - Phonorecords
    - "Over the Rainbow" and "Let's catch a star," 45 RPM, Cricket Records (Oversize 2)
    - "We're off to see the Wizard" and "The Thank you song," 45 RPM, Cricket Records (Oversize 2)
  - Book poster for The Wonderful Wizard of Oz, ca. 1900 (Oversize 3)
  - The Baum Bugle, 1962; 2 copies (Oversize 3)
  - Poster for Hungry Tiger of Oz (Oversize 4)
  - Wooden models
    - Scarecrow of Oz (Oversize 4)
    - Patchwork Girl of Oz (Oversize 5)
  - Book jackets, 28 items (Oversize 6)
  - Photostats of newsclips (Oversize 7)
  - Scrapbook - press material on To Please a Child (Oversize 8)
  - MGM press material on Wizard of Oz (Oversize 9)
  - Photostats from Chicago Record-Herald comic section (Oversize 10)
  - Posters - Oz titles (Oversize 11)
  - Photostats - Baum stories appearing in newspapers (Oversize 12)
  - Proof sheets Oz characters (Oversize 13)
- Books
  Item level records for the many Oz books in our collection are not included in this finding aid. To see a complete list of all books by L. Frank Baum, please consult the library's main catalog, SUMMIT (accessible here). Search for "Baum, L. Frank" and select "*Author" under "Search By."